Guide to the Book Trade Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Book trade collection
1729-1812
OSB MSS 33
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
Receipts and short notes concerning the book trade in London in the late 18th and early 19th centuries. Booksellers include Thomas Caddell, Thomas Longman, Thomas Lowndes, George Nicol, John Nourse, Paul Vaillant, Thomas Vernor, John Whiston, and John Wilkie. There is one long letter from Andrew Millar to David Mallet about the sales of Mallet's edition of the works of Henry St. John, Lord Viscount Bolingbroke.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to the book trade.
Booksellers and bookselling -- Great Britain; Receipts (financial records) -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Receipts (financial records) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Booksellers; Caddell, Thomas, 1742-1802; Longman, Thomas, 1731-1797; Lowndes, Thomas, 1719-1784; Mallet, David, 1705?-1765; Millar, Andrew, 1705-1768; Nicol, G. (George), 1740?-1828; Nourse, John, 1762?-1790; Vaillant, Paul, -1802; Vernor, Thomas, -1793; Whiston, John, 1711-1780; Wilkie, J. (John), -1785
- Correspondence and Receipts, 1796 Apr 5
  - Adams, H. Receipt to Vernor & Hood, signed, 1796 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baillie, Alex. ALS to Thomas Cadell, 1780 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baker, Samuel, ca. 1712-1778. Receipt, signed, 1769 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    On an account to John Nourse for books supplied to John Nourse by Baker and Leigh.
  - Baldwin, Richard. Receipt, signed, 1746 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    To John Nourse for binding two books.
  - Barnard, Frederick. ALS to Mr. Nicolls, 1781 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baumgarten, F. E. Statement of account to Mr. Phillips for books., 1782 Jan (Box 1, Folder 6)
    List included.
  - Becket, Thomas, fl. 1760-1776. ALS to unnamed recipient, 1760 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Requests a copy of Robertson's History.
  - Bladon, Samuel, d. 1779. ALS to unnamed recipient, 1760 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Blair, Ann (Persode)
    - ALS to Thomas Cadell, Downing St., 1783 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - LS and AL (3d person) to Mr. [Robert?] Lawless, 1794 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Concerns several works by John Blair.
  - Blair, John, d. 1782. Receipt, signed, 1774 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    To Thomas Cadell for £24 for 6 copies of his work on Chronological and Historical Tables.
  - Bowyer, Robert, 1758-1834. 2 Receipts, signed, 1793 Jun, Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
    To Mr. Boydell acknowledging payment for a copy of Complete History of England.
  - Buckland, James, 1710-1790. 2 ALS to Thomas Cadell, 1773 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Requests copies of several works.
  - Cadell, Elizabeth. Signature, cut from a letter, Bellsize Lane, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cadell, Thomas, 1742-1802. ALS (fragment) to unnamed recipient, London, 1772 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cadell, William. ALS (fragment) to Andrew Miller, Bristol, 1765 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cadell & Davies, publishers. Memorandum (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Concerning printing costs for an unidentified pamphlet. Manuscript in an unidentified hand.
  - Chambers, Frances, Lady. ALS to unnamed recipient, Putney, [1814-20] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Corbett, Charles. Receipt, signed, [n.y.] Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    To John Nourse, acknowledging payment for items sold.
  - Dashwood, A., Lady. AL (3d person) to Mr. Evans [Thomas?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Davis, Charles, d. 1755
    - Receipt, signed, to John Nourse, 1747 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Acknowledging payment for books sold.
    - Receipt, signed, to John Nourse, 1747 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Douglas, John, Bp. of Salisbury, 1721-1807. ALS to unnamed recipient, Windsor Castle, 1790 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Requests a copy of a work by Charles Alexander de Calonne.
  - Duncan, J. ALS to [Thomas Cadell?], 1774 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elmsly, Peter, 1736-1802
    - Document, signed, for P. Elmsly, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Receipt, signed, for a shipment of books, 1782 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Receipt, signed, to John Gill for settlement of George Keith's account, 1783 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Glover, Richard, 1712-1785. ALS to Thomas Becket, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Grant, Lady. AL (3d person) to William Strahan, Pall Mall, [n.y.] May 17 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Grantham, Thomas Robinson, 2d Baron, 1738-1786. AL (3d person) to unnamed recipient, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hamilton, Lane. ALS to unnamed recipient, 1801 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hurd, Richard, Bp. of Worcester, 1720-1808. 2 ALS to Cadell & Davies, 1795 May 20, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Jephson, William. Receipt, signed, to Jacob Tonson for wines sold, 1729 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kearsley, George. ALS to Thomas Cadell, 1791 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Asks for a copy of Hugh Blair's sermons.
  - Lawless, Robert. ALS (fragment) to unnamed recipient, 1783 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    For Thomas Cadell.
  - Longman, Thomas, 1699-1755
    - ALS to John Nourse, 1746 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Receipt, signed, to John Nourse, acknowledging payment for book sold, 1750 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Longman, Thomas, 1730-1797. Memorandum, holograph, signed, 1775 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Millar, Andrew, 1707-1768. AL (draft) to [David Mallet?], Kew Garden, [1762] Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Concerns the poor sale of Bolingbroke's Works.
  - Morgan, Mr. AL (3d person) to Thomas Cadell, Bride St., [n.y.] May 27 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mortimer, Thomas, 1730-1810. Receipt, signed, to George Robinson, 1784 Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Concerning a new edition of Every Man his Own Broker.
  - Murray, S. Receipt, signed, to Vernor & Hood, 1796 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Nicol, George, 1741-1829
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1781 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Mentions James Robson.
    - Promissory note, signed to James Dodsley for £26.12.4, 1779 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Receipt, signed, to John Nourse, 1759 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Nourse, John, d. 1780
    - ALS to Francis [Wingrave?], [n.p.], 1775 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Tells him to pay Mr. Hamilton Sr. £100.
    - Promissory note, signed to Benjamin Cole for £20, 1745/6 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Memorandum of agreement between John Nourse and Richard Montagu, 1747 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Also signed by Montagu.
    - 2 ANS to him, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Osborne, Thomas d. 1743. ALS to John Nourse, 1732 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Osborne, Thomas, d. 1767. ALS to Andrew Millar, [London], 1760 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Requests several books.
  - Pennant, Thomas, 1726-1798. ALS to Thomas Cadell, Downing, 1785 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Letter discusses a work by de Buffon.
  - Pratt, Samuel Jackson, 1749-1814. ALS (signed by Courtney Melmoth) to Thomas Cadell, Bath, 1778 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Rivington, Charles, 1688-1742. Receipt, signed, to John Nourse, for payment for books purchased, 1736 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Sastres, F. AL (3d person) to Rudolph Ackermann, London, 1809 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Concerns his Repository of the Arts, & c.
  - Say, Edward, d. 1769. Receipt (holograph, signed) to John Nourse, for £50 payment for a share in the General Evening Post, 1750-51 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Seward, William, 1747-1799
    - 2 ALS and 1 memorandum to Cadell & Davies, 1795 Jul, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - 2 ALS to Thomas Davies, [1795 Jun 30], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Stanhope, Grizel (Hamilton) Stanhope, Countess, d. 1811. ALS and AL to unnamed recipients, Ovenden, 1799 May, 1800 May (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Tighe, S. ALS to Thomas Cadell, Harrow, 1786 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Tonson & Co. Receipt (signed John Hardy) to Sir John Evelyn for payment for books supplied, 1753 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Vaillant, Paul, d. 1802
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1791 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Requests a copy of Malone's Shakespeare.
    - Receipt, signed, to Sir John Evelyn for payment for books, 1755 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Vincent, G. AL (3d person) to Cadell & Davies, 1812 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Concerns an advertisement to be placed in the Morning Chronicle and Morning Herald.
  - Watson, Jonathan, Bp. of St. Andrews, d. 1809. ALS to Thomas Cadell, 1794 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Wetsteins & Smith, firm, Amsterdam. Document, signed: bill of exchange to John Nourse concerning payment to Mr. Roeland Van Thiel, 1731 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Whiston, John, d. 1780
    - ALS to Andrew Millar, 1753 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      Mentions an agreement with Messrs. Tonson and Watts.
    - Receipt, signed, to Sir John Evelyn for payment for books bought from Whiston and White, 1753 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - White, Benjamin, d. 1794. Receipt, signed, to Sir John Evelyn for payment for books purchased from Whiston and White, 1754 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Wilkie, John, d. 1785
    - Receipt, signed, to Thomas Lowndes acknowledging payment for list of books, 1763 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      List and prices included.
    - Receipt, signed, to Thomas Lowndes acknowledging payment for a list of books, 1770 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Wilmot, Samuel. ALS to John Nourse, Oxford, 1738 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Unidentifed order and receipt (Box 1, Folder 73)